Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Staff meeting minutes, 1927-1938, 1951-1952 and undated RL.00749
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Use Copies, 1927-1938, 1951-1952 and undated; 1
  - Creative Organization Staff Meetings, 1932-1934; 3
    - 1932 Nov. 16 (Box 6)
      Baltimore City Baking; Chase & Sanborn's Tea; scientific investigation; American Medical Association; General Motors; Therese Olzendam; employment of science in advertising; William Day; Therese Olzendam
    - 1932 Nov. 23 (Box 6)
      Legal phases of advertising; "Lying and Stealing"--Misrepresentation; defamation; right of privacy; appropriation of property rights
    - 1932 Dec. 7 (Box 6)
      Rowntree Candies of Canada; impressions of Hollywood; Ruth Waldo; Savington Crampton
    - 1932 Dec. 14 (Box 6)
      French's Mustard; Fifth Avenue Week; 5th Avenue Association; retail window displays; Ruth Waldo; Alice Coester; Patricia Krell
    - 1932 Dec. 21 (Box 6)
      Radio Department; Brer Rabbit Molasses; Royal Baking Powder; Davey Tree Surgery; Vigoro; Fleischmann's Yeast; William Day; John Reber
    - 1933 Jan. 12 (Box 6)
      Technocracy; economic theory; Quincy Howe (editor, Living Age); Howard Scott (founder of technocracy movement); "Technocracy" (Living Age); "Facts and Threats of Technocracy" (Iron Age)
    - 1933 Jan. 25 (Box 6)
      Technocratic theories; John Herbert Van Deventer (editor, Iron Age)
    - 1933 Feb. 1 (Box 6)
      Experiences in Russia; photography; Margaret Bourke-White
    - 1933 Feb. 8 (Box 6)
      Tower Magazine Group; F.W. Woolworth stores; middle-class families; retail store development; Catherine McNelis (publisher, Tower Magazines)
    - 1933 Feb. 15 (Box 6)
      Techniques of photography; Helen Smith
    - 1933 Mar. 1 (Box 7)
      Premiums in advertising and selling schemes; Tiger Coal
    - 1933 Mar. 8 (Box 7)
      Advertising during a depression; Thomas McLaughlin (Saturday Evening Post)
    - 1933 Mar. 15 (Box 7)
      Merchandising; the function of a research department; Lloyd Baillie
    - 1933 Mar. 23 (Box 7)
      Comic and cartoon art; Jacob Gortatowsky (Hearst Comics)
    - 1933 Mar. 29 (Box 7)
      New business activities; William Palmer; Erwin Wasey
    - 1933 Apr. 12 (Box 7)
      Newspaper and specialty features; Ward Greene (King Features)
    - 1933 Apr. 19 (Box 7)
      Current advertising problems: sales; store displays; media Lloyd Baillie
    - 1933 Apr. 26 (Box 7)
      Sales statistics in advertising; advertising terrorities; advertising copy testing; Lloyd Baillie
    - 1933 May 3 (Box 7)
      Radio advertising; radio rusic; Russell Bennett
    - 1933 May 10 (Box 7)
      Federal Trade Commission; misleading advertising; advertising testimonials; Food and Drug Act; Dr. John A. Killian; the application of research in biochemistry to manufacturing and advertising; Dana Ackerly (Breed, Abbott & Morgan)
    - 1934 Jan. 3 (Box 7)
      Consumer reactions at World's Fair; Rohe Walter; Daniel Starch
    - 1934 Feb. 7 (Box 7)
      Dr. Daniel Starch's Advertising Service; quantitative analysis of magazine readers; Claude Hooper (Daniel Starch)
    - 1934 Feb. 21 (Box 7)
      Argentina; Arthur Farlow (JWT Buenos Aires)
    - 1934 Oct. 11 (Box 7)
      Fanny A. Bell's speech on legal issues in advertising
    - Indexes, 1932-1934 (Box 7)
  - JWT Forum, 1934-1938; 4
    The JWT Forum represented a resumption of the Creative Organization staff meetings. The new meetings, attended by top company officials and the creative staff, were held bi-weekly and featured lectures by staff members. Discussions included advertising practices, client campaigns, activities of domestic branch offices, and legal aspects of advertising. [Source: Accession records]
    - 1936 Jan. 7 (Box 7)
      "Bad Taste in Advertising"--Wallace Boren
    - 1936 Jan. 21 (Box 7)
      "Is Advertising Honest?"--William Palmer
    - 1936 Feb. 4 (Box 7)
      "Is Advertising Copy in a Period of Decadence?"--Henry Legler
    - 1936 Mar. 3 (Box 7)
      "The Natural-Born Salesman"--Henry Flower
    - 1936 May 12 (Box 7)
      "Premiums"--Russell Pierce
    - 1936 Oct. 20 (Box 7)
      "Regaining Lost Leadership"--William Day
    - 1936 Nov. 3 (Box 7)
      "Ballantine"--William McKeehan
    - 1936 Nov. 18 (Box 7)
      "Nobody Reads the Copy"--Henry Legler
    - 1936 Dec. 1 (Box 7)
      Outdoor advertising; George Diebert; Elwood Whitney
    - 1936 Dec. 15 (Box 7)
      Eastman Kodak Company; Thayer Jaccaci
    - 1937 Jan. 12 (Box 7)
      Emerson Drug Company; Philip Richardson
    - 1937 Feb. 23 (Box 7)
      "Speaking for the Company"--Lynn Baker
    - 1937 Mar. 9 (Box 7)
      J. B. Williams Company; William Resor
    - 1937 Mar. 23 (Box 7)
      "Analysis of the Urban versus the Rural Markets of the United States"--Arno Johnson
    - 1937 Apr. 6 (Box 7)
      "Advertising Roots Go Deep"--Howard Henderson
    - 1937 Apr. 20 (Box 7)
      "The Robertson-Patman Act"--Russell Pierce
    - 1937 June 9 (Box 7)
      "Shell's 1937 Dealer Slide Film"--Steve Kenyon
    - 1937 Nov. 9 (Box 7)
      Lever Brothers; William Palmer
    - 1937 Nov. 23 (Box 7)
      "A Discussion of Consumer Premiums"--John Hosch Jr.
    - 1937 Dec. 7 (Box 7)
      "Apology for Today in Advertising"--William Day
    - 1938 Jan. 8 (Box 8)
      Discussion of the current status and future possibilities of commercial motion pictures--Fred Fidler
    - 1938 Feb. 1 (Box 8)
      "Commercial Movies"--Fred Fidler
    - 1938 Mar. 11 (Box 8)
      "Copy Testing"--James Young
    - 1938 May 10 (Box 8)
      "The Wheeler Lee Bill"--Dr. John A. Killian
    - 1938 Oct. 7 (Box 8)
      "Life Under the Federal Trade Commission"--Fanny Bell
    - Separated attachments to minutes, 1934-1936 (Oversize-folder 1)
      Materials removed from meetings of Feb. 4 and Mar. 3: Advertisements for Fleischmann's Yeast (1936) and Woodbury Facial Soap (1936); H.E. Ingram Longwear Shoes Sales-Mover sales talking points bulletin (1934).
  - Monday Evening Staff Meetings, 1930; 5
    Monday Evening Meetings were enrichment lectures given by outside speakers and presented each week from March through May 1930 in the JWT Assembly Hall. Speakers included editors and publishers, Clarence Darrow, Rudy Vallee, and Will Hays, the motion picture censor. Stanley Resor also gave one talk regarding his trip to the JWt west coast branch offices.
    - 1930 Mar. 3 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Mr. Harcourt, President of Harcourt, Brace & Company"; the public's reaction to books; Alfred Harcourt
    - 1930 Mar. 10 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Mr. Joseph P. Day, President of Joseph P. Day Realty Company"; personal experiences in real estate
    - 1930 Mar. 17 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Merrill Goddard"; mentality of today and its origins in antiquity
    - 1930 Mar. 24 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Mr. James Quirk, Editor of Photoplay Magazine"; psychology of the motion picture in relation to advertising
    - 1930 Mar. 31 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Rudy Vallee"; study of the American public
    - 1930 Apr. 7 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by William Chennery, Editor of Collier's Weekly"; Collier's weekly and what Chennery did to revive it
    - 1930 Apr. 14 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Mr. Stanley Resor, President of the J. Walter Thompson Company"; JWT California Office
    - 1930 Apr. 28 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Mr. Clarence Darrow"; autobiography and personal philosophy
    - 1930 May 5 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by 'Roxy' Mr. Samuel L. Rothapfel"; ideas of motion picture theater and showmanship
    - 1930 May 12 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Mr. Will Hays"; Standards of motion picture production
    - 1930 May 19 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Mr. Isaac Marcosson of the Saturday Evening Post"; interviewing prominent persons
    - 1930 May 26 (Box 8)
      "A Talk Given by Mr. Loring A Schuler, Editor of the Ladies Home Journal"; Editorial policy of the Ladies Home Journal
    - Index, 1930 (Box 8)
  - Men's and Women's Apprentice Groups, 1936-1937; 6
    The Men's Apprentice Group, composed of new employees at the JWT New York Office, was established in 1935. Members of the group attended weekly luncheon meetings chaired by Howard Kohl and generally featured a company speaker, frequently Fanny Bell of the Research Department. The group also published a bi-weekly newsletter from 1935-1938 originally called the Junior News Letter and then the Flash. A Women's Apprentice Group was founded in 1937. [Source: Accession records.]
    - 1936 Sept. 4 (Box 8)
      Speech by Fanny A. Bell; "Future Vice Presidents of What-You-Will!"
    - 1937 Mar. 12 (Box 8)
      Speech by Fanny A. Bell; Legal Department
  - Chicago Junior Forum, 1951-1952; undated; 7
    The JWT Junior Forum was a lecture series held during 1951 and 1952 in the Chicago Office. Executives of JWT spoke at periodic luncheon meetings to "younger members of the organization." Topics of these lectures included JWT history, the advertising industry, the functions of specific departments, advertising techniques, and client case studies. [Source: Accession records.]
    - 1951 Jan. 17 (Box 8)
      General background on the agency business and J. Walter Thompson Company in particular--George Reeves
    - 1951 Jan. 31 (Box 8)
      Principles of copywriting from the JWT standpoint--Kenneth Ward
    - 1951 Feb. 14 (Box 8)
      What is an advertising executive?--Alexander Gunn
    - 1951 Feb. 28 (Box 8)
      Art direction--General--Frederick Boulton
    - 1951 Mar. 14 (Box 8)
      Research Department functions and methods--H.C. Campbell
    - 1951 Mar. 28 (Box 8)
      Media Department functions--George Pearson
    - 1951 Apr. 11 (Box 8)
      Mechanical production--E. Thomas McBreen
    - 1951 Apr. 25 (Box 8)
      Public Relations-Publicity Department--C. Stuart Siebert Jr.
    - 1951 May (Box 8)
      Testing advertising
    - 1951 May 9 (Box 8)
      Traffic control system--Ward Weist
    - 1951 May 23 (Box 8)
      Electronic advertising media--Hal Rorke
    - 1951 June 6 (Box 8)
      Production of TV commercials--Peter Cavallo Jr.
    - 1951 July 5 (Box 8)
      Home Economics Department--Mabel Anderson
    - 1951 July 18 (Box 8)
      Media Department, outdoor advertising--C.J. Keenan
    - 1951 Aug. 1 (Box 8)
      Merchandising--Charles Holcomb
    - 1951 Aug. 15 (Box 8)
      The J. Walter Thompson Company Consumer Purchase Panel--W.S. O'Donnell
    - 1951 Sept. 5 (Box 8)
      Are copywriters born that way?--Elizabeth Blackman
    - 1951 Sept. 19 (Box 8)
      Radio and Television time-buying--Edward Fitzgerald
    - 1951 Oct. 3 (Box 8)
      Art techniques in advertising--Lou Ingwersen
    - 1951 Oct. 31 (Box 8)
      Case history of Kraft De Luxe Slices--Thomas Wason
    - 1951 Nov. 28 (Box 8)
      Case history of Window Shade Institute campaigns--Theodore Weldon
    - 1952 Apr. 2 (Box 8)
      What is advertising and why do people advertise?--C.S. Lund
    - 1952 Apr. 16 (Box 8)
      The "which", "why" and "when" of contests and premiums--Allen Center
    - 1952 May 14 (Box 9)
      Creative process in the television film commercial--Otis Carney
    - 1952 June 25 (Box 9)
      Newspapers as an advertising medium--A.G. Ensrud
    - 1952 Dec. 10 (Box 9)
      Case study of Libby--Theodore Jardine
    - undated (Box 9)
      The JWT-Chicago Television-Radio-Film Department--Peter Cavallo Jr.
    - undated (Box 9)
      Another problem solved by advertising